IAN NELSON

50 Arundel Beach Rd., Severna Park MD, 21146

PHONE 479.567.6622

E-MAIL iannelson1@gmail.com



SUMMARY

Full-stack software engineer with over 15 years of development and analysis experience solving some of the nation's most difficult problems inside of the Intelligence Community and U.S. Military. I pride myself on work ethic, a consistent commitment to learning new technologies and am passionate about working on challenging problems with others.

SKILLS

- Eloquent writer, speaker and presenter.
- Quick to learn business processes, systems, and architectures in a new environment.
- Able to communicate effectively between business, technical, and sales staff members.
- Quick to provide training and mentorship to junior members of the team.
- Fluent and practiced in Agile/Scrum project methodologies (Certified ScrumMaster cert.)
- Able to participate as an individual team contributor or manage teams where needed.
- Practiced "outside the box" thinker.

SOFTWARE

JavaScript / Node.js HTML5 / Web Libs. Java

Scala Python

Linux Systems / CLI Spark / Hadoop

Ansible
OpenStack/ AWS

Git + GitHub Workflow



EDUCATION

University of Maryland, University College

B.S. in Computer Science

January 2010 - May 2012

Adelphi, MD

Nominated to Dean's List every enrolled semester, and invited to join Sigma Alpha Pi as an honor student. Graduated with Honors (Cum Laude, 3.75 GPA)

Arkansas Tech University

August 2007 - December 2008

B.S. in Computer Science

Russellville, AR

Served as a team leader and university representative for Association for Computing Machinery (ACM) software development competitions. Also served as an official tutor for the Computer Science department, mentoring more than 30 students in basic and advanced computer science concepts, data structures, and principals of mathematical application.

EXPERIENCE

IronNet Cybersecurity

October 2014 to Present

Senior Software Engineer

Fulton, MD

- Technical lead for streaming analytics effort. This product capability was implemented using data from a distributed Kafka bus to Spark Streaming. This architecture served as an interface to models performing unsupervised learning in near real-time.
- Served as the technical oversight staff member for the president of the company's Technical
 Division. This effort was critical in identifying technical issues during system and software
 integration as appliances were deployed into customer environments. In addition, worked
 with members of all component development teams and infrastructure personnel to adjust
 software design and implementation mechanics, ultimately leading to better continuous
 deployment.
- Designed and implemented several prototypes of a large-scale node graph visualization (100K+ nodes), giving full network situational awareness as a next-generation capability.
- Designed and implemented the first prototype and implementation of the product's user interface and RESTful API. Used a combination of AngularJS, Node.js, MongoDB and WebSockets to produce a fully streaming architecture to receive information and alerts from the product processing pipeline.

Clarity Innovations

June 2015 to Present

Member, Technical Advisory Board

Columbia, MD

- Assisted company executives in determining common technology trends to efficiently execute multiple contracts using a single development implementation.
- Worked with executive team to assist in contract acquisition and business analysis.

National Security Agency

April 2012 to October 2014

Technical Director

Fort Meade, MD

- Led three teams of 70+ software engineers developing OZONE Platform and the OZONE
 Widget Framework. This software was instrumental in government use by multiple agencies
 (Intelligence Community, U.S. Military, Social Security Administration, etc.) to conduct
 integration activities at a low-cost through an easy to use web application framework.
- Led the technical effort to implement the Intelligence Community (IC) Application Mall as part
 of the IC IT Enterprise activity to consolidate common infrastructure across agencies. Worked
 to solve elastic architectures needed to support Internet-scale user loads, and additionally
 worked with ODNI technical staff to ensure security mechanisms supported multi-agency
 access.
- Worked with network engineers to produce open-source prototype SDN controllers and enable collaboration between government, industry, and academic partners.